

Michael Newham

Helping businesses to survive, thrive, innovate & collaborate!

Address: 4 Sandymount Avenue, Birr, Co. Offaly, R42 A972.

Website: https://www.linkedin.com/in/michaelnewham/

Email: mail2mick@gmail.com

<< Working on: - SFI funded > NAPSS (autonomous pods); EU funded CASP-CADE (designing self-driving car);
Prepping for: - Climate Action Fund project M-MAF (Micro-Mobility Advanced Manufacturing) >>

Advisor - to great businesses for research, training & development needs.

Mentor - for high potential start-ups re: funding, finance & investment requirements.

Networker - amongst teams for programming, promotion and management of events.

Business Development - Over 20 years experience in business ownership, collaborative research and event management. Primarily interested in the use of technology to create opportunities, reduce consumption and maintain a healthy quality of life.

European Research Projects - Experience in coordinating, writing, researching and completing projects in time and on budget.

Training & Event Management - Knowledge in compilation of course schedules, speaker engagement and workshop delivery.

Funding & Operations - Thorough understanding of the Irish & European funding & finance ecosystem - the 'oil' that fuels the growth and eventual success of any business.

EXPERIENCE

App AdvisorFunding, Research & Training Consultant

Jul 2017 to Present

Apr 2017 to Present

Fellow management consultant at AppAdvisor.ie for tech. companies.

- Michael works alongside Joe Connaughton at 'AppAdvisor' to assist companies on opportunities to save cash; attract finance & go LEAN in their day-to-day operations.
- Michael's particular expertise focuses on funding applications, workshop training and investigation of export opportunities in the light of Brexit.

Red Apple Cáfe

Business Owner

Co-owner at this award winning café.

- Based in Birr, Offaly 'The Red Apple' delivers high quality food to both tourists and discerning locals.
- n Michael deals with the business side re: wages, VAT returns, tax filings, supplier payments etc.

Mobility Mojo Jan 2016 to Mar 2017

Funding Director

Mobility Mojo, a Richard Branson backed company (http://bit.ly/33ypp94) - has the mission to mainstream accessibility by removing the fear and awkwardness around it.

- "Deep down everyone is open to the world. We just want to make sure that the world is open to everyone".
- Was responsible for seeking funding & investment for this fledgling start-up. Won Enterprise Ireland CSF, NDRC - Accelerator, Social Entrepreneurs Ireland - Elevator; to name but a few.

Mover (P2P CarSharing)

Built an innovative platform that allowed folk to rent their own car out to their neighbours and friends.

- Mover's vision was to have a 'shared car on every street' in our country.
- Winner of 'frontierCities' funding to the tune of €150K and LIT Ladder funding of €25K.
- Unfortunately, we couldn't get the right insurance to successfully launch!

North Tipperary Green Enterprise Park Limited (WeCreate WorkSpace)

Aug 2008 to Mar 2017

Founder & Operations Director

Co-founder who applied for and won Enterprise Ireland 'Community Enterprise Centre' funding.

- This covered costs for building construction & infrastructure. Also won funding from Clann Credo and Tipperary LEO for the kitting out of Ireland's first FabLab (Fabrication Laboratory).
- Managed relationships with a variety of state bodies including Enterprise Ireland, Tipperary LEO and Tipperary County Council.
- Helped research, procure and set-up hot-desking, digital fabrication equipment, training courses, mentoring & project incubation services. All as part of the 'WeCreate WorkSpace Innovation Hub'.

GoCar CarSharing Limited

Sep 2008 to Dec 2014

Founder & Operations Director

Co-founded, operated and sold Ireland's first car-sharing service.

- Oversaw implementation of our 'GoCar' pay-by-the-hour hire service to new sites in Dublin and Cork.
- Selected and commissioned low emission diesel models. Responsible for fleet operations, data logging, customer billing, car location vetting and business growth strategy.
- Subscribe and drive! You can join GoCar as a customer; providing you with 24/7 access to our growing fleet of cars. Book online or from your phone and have instant access to any of these vehicles.
- Partner amongst multiple organisations in collaborative research programs such as MoMo CarSharing (http://www.momo-cs.eu).

Sustainable Projects Ireland Ltd (Cloughjordan EcoVillage)

Jan 2002 to Aug 2008

Founder & Sales Director

Co-founder and Sales Director of Cloughjordan EcoVillage project - www.TheVillage.ie.

- Involved in the conceptual planning and design of a new sustainable community while also guiding members to their new home in Cloughjordan, Tipperary.
- The award winning sustainable development brought together cutting-edge technologies; green building techniques; renewable energy production; multiple enterprises and the latest in community design.
- Responsible for the research, design and implementation of the sales and marketing strategy leading to plot sales of circa €5m.
- Co-wrote multiple funding applications for AIB, Clann Credo Finance etc as well as provision of research for European collaborative projects.

Intel Ireland, Cornmarket Financial Services Ireland, Logica Ireland

Jun 1995 to Dec 2001

Various Tech. Roles; Systems Engineer, Network Administrator, Quality Auditor, etc.

Systems Engineer @ Logica Ireland

Responsible for computer network covering four sites and 200 PC's +. Implemented upgrade of network infrastructure from token-ring to ethernet.

Set-up server backups with off-site data recovery enabled. General 'go-to' person for PC and Laptop issues.

- Systems Administrator @ Cornmarket Financial Services Ireland Network maintenance, Hot-desk support, Printer maintenance, Server backups etc.
- Quality Auditor @ Intel Ireland Oversaw quality issues on daily shifts in the motherboard processing facility.

EDUCATION

National University of Ireland, Galway

2017 to 2018

Post-Graduate Diploma in TechInnovation: 2:1

TechInnovate is a unique team-based technology innovation fellowship at NUI Galway, where teams identify real needs in a certain domain and invent/implement solutions. This fellowship has been established to inspire and create the next generation of techpreneurs (entrepreneurial technologists), forming new companies and strengthening existing ones. High-calibre Fellows are recruited to form 2–3 person interdisciplinary teams and participate in an intensive 10-month programme that goes from concept to product.

University of Limerick

2010 to 2011

E-Learning: Design & Development

The purpose of this programme is to equip graduates with the skills needed to design and develop multimedia content and technology-enhanced learning solutions.

The need for this type of expertise is expanding rapidly as more and more companies and institutions use information and communication technologies (ICTs).

Irish Management Institute

2009 to 2010

Innovation for Growth

The Irish Management Institute (IMI) has partnered with Enterprise Ireland to deliver Innovation 4 Growth. This is a unique programme specifically designed to meet the needs of ambitious and entrepreneurial Irish companies who seek to use innovation as a way to unlock opportunities in the marketplace.

It allows the management team of an organisation the opportunity to take time out to focus on how they may drive the organisations growth through innovation.

All Hallows College

1997 to 2002

Bachelor's Degree

Main degree in Psychology and Theology.

Irish / Swiss Institute of Horology

1992 to 1995

Apprenticeship in Watchmaking:

This three year full-time apprenticeship in watchmaking - provided me the technical skills to start a career in computer assembly and operations that I than began with Intel Ireland.

VOLUNTEER EXPERIENCE

The Growery

2016 to Present

Board Member

The award winning social ecology project - 'The Growery' - is a not-for-profit enterprise based in the heart of Birr Town, Co. Offaly. Michael helps craft funding applications while assisting on the programming & delivery of multiple food growing / community resilience workshops. Also involved in the day-to-day propagation, weeding and watering of the veggies!

Theosophical Society in Ireland

1994 to Present

Member of the Board of Trustees

A long time trustee to the society's assets and property in Dublin 4, Ireland. Responsible for accounts oversight and ensuring expenditure remains aligned with the organisations values and ethos.

REFERENCES

Referee details can be sent upon request.